Hello and welcome. In the previous episode we discussed container networking interface or CNI
안녕하세요, 환영합니다. 이전 에피소드에서는 컨테이너 네트워킹 인터페이스 또는 CNI에 대해 설명했습니다.
and pod networking. We also discussed flannel CNI in the context of Kubernetes in some details.
와 파드 네트워킹에 대해 알아보았다. 또한 쿠버네티스의 맥락에서 플란넬 CNI에 대해 자세히 설명했습니다.
We'll continue that trend and today we'll discuss another popular CNI provider called Calico.
이러한 추세를 이어가면서 오늘은 또 다른 인기 있는 CNI 제공업체인 Calico에 대해 알아보겠습니다.
We'll gain detailed level understanding of how Calico works and how operationally it differs
Calico의 작동 방식과 운영상의 차이점에 대해 자세히 알아보겠습니다.
from flannel. In case you missed my previous presentation on CNI, I'm going to discuss this
플란넬에서. CNI에 대한 이전 프레젠테이션을 놓치신 분들을 위해 이에 대해 다시 설명하겠습니다.
in some overview in the next couple of screens. So basically CNI is really an open source
다음 두 화면에서 간략하게 설명하겠습니다. 기본적으로 CNI는 오픈 소스입니다.
software that provides network plumbing for containers. As containers becomes popular
컨테이너를 위한 네트워크 배관을 제공하는 소프트웨어입니다. 컨테이너가 대중화됨에 따라
then it becomes evident that you know every software has to do the same thing to set up
모든 소프트웨어가 설정을 위해 동일한 작업을 수행해야 한다는 것이 분명해졌습니다.
networking, assign IP addresses and so on and that becomes really tedious and repetitive.
네트워킹, IP 주소 할당 등 모든 소프트웨어가 동일한 작업을 수행해야 한다는 것을 알게 되면 정말 지루하고 반복적인 작업이 됩니다.
And this project basically creates provides a service to containers so any software that deals
그리고 이 프로젝트는 기본적으로 컨테이너에 서비스를 제공하기 때문에 컨테이너를 다루는 모든 소프트웨어는
with containers such as Kubernetes, Cloud Foundry, Podman and etc can take advantage of
쿠버네티스, 클라우드 파운드리, 팟맨 등과 같은 컨테이너를 다루는 모든 소프트웨어가 활용할 수 있다.
the CNI interface that they provide. So let's see quickly and graphically how CNI works.
이 제공하는 CNI 인터페이스를 활용할 수 있습니다. 그럼 이제 CNI가 어떻게 작동하는지 그래픽으로 빠르게 살펴보겠습니다.
So what I'm showing here is we have a server. This is a node, a Kubernetes node and the entire
여기서 보여드리는 것은 서버가 있다는 것입니다. 이것은 노드, 쿠버네티스 노드, 그리고 전체
thing is one server and we have API Kubernetes services installed and we also have a network
는 하나의 서버이며, API 쿠버네티스 서비스가 설치되어 있고 네트워크도 있습니다.
namespace. So the network namespace really anytime you create a Linux host it actually
네임스페이스도 있습니다. 따라서 네트워크 네임스페이스는 실제로 리눅스 호스트를 생성할 때마다
what is called a default network namespace. Network space is basically a container and
를 기본 네트워크 네임스페이스라고 합니다. 네트워크 공간은 기본적으로 컨테이너이며
that anything or everything just had anything to do with the network such as the IP address,
IP 주소 등 네트워크와 관련된 모든 것을 저장할 수 있습니다,
the interface, the ethernet interface, the firewall rules, the routes, everything. So
인터페이스, 이더넷 인터페이스, 방화벽 규칙, 경로, 모든 것이요. 그래서
those are really containing what is called a network namespace. So once we want to create,
이것들은 실제로 네트워크 네임스페이스라고 불리는 것을 포함하고 있습니다. 따라서 일단 생성하고 싶으면
we want to deploy a Kubernetes pod. So the API server calls into kubelet service.
를 생성한 후, 쿠버네티스 파드를 배포하려고 합니다. 그래서 API 서버가 kubelet 서비스를 호출합니다.
kubelet service then calls into CNI plugin and that's where it creates a pod network namespace
그런 다음 kubelet 서비스가 CNI 플러그인을 호출하고 여기에서 파드 네트워크 네임스페이스를 생성한다.
like the one that we have here. Now the pod has its own name namespace. Then it installs
와 같은 네임스페이스를 생성합니다. 이제 파드에 고유한 네임스페이스가 생겼습니다. 그런 다음 설치한다.
a virtual ethernet interface that comes in pairs. So one pair would be one side of the pair would be
쌍으로 제공되는 가상 이더넷 인터페이스를 설치합니다. 따라서 한 쌍의 한쪽은 다음과 같다.
inside the namespace and the other part is actually created and attached to the host.
에 있고 다른 한쪽은 실제로 생성되어 호스트에 연결됩니다.
And that is a pipeline that provides communication between the host and the pod.
그리고 이것이 호스트와 파드 간의 통신을 제공하는 파이프라인이다.
It all then assigns an IP address to that pod. It also sets the default route and that is how
그런 다음 해당 파드에 IP 주소를 할당한다. 또한 기본 경로를 설정하며 다음과 같이 한다.
the communication with the outside world needs to go, what routes it will need to take. It also
외부 세계와의 통신이 어떤 경로를 통해 이루어져야 하는지를 결정합니다. 또한
does the same thing on the host and it adds the routes to the container. So now we have
은 호스트에서 동일한 작업을 수행하여 컨테이너에 경로를 추가합니다. 이제 우리는
established a communication between the host and the container.
호스트와 컨테이너 간의 통신이 설정되었습니다.
Now that we have some understanding of how CNI plugins work, let's talk about Calico,
이제 CNI 플러그인의 작동 방식을 어느 정도 이해했으니, Calico에 대해 이야기해 보겠습니다,
which is a very popular CNI plugin provider. In the previous episode, we discussed Flannel.
에 대해 알아보겠습니다. 이전 에피소드에서는 플란넬에 대해 설명했습니다.
So to install Calico, once you set up your initial Kubernetes cluster, then you can run
따라서 캘리코를 설치하려면, 초기 쿠버네티스 클러스터를 설정한 다음
kubectl apply minus f and this is the URL to where the installation package is.
kubectl apply에서 f를 빼면 설치 패키지가 있는 곳의 URL이 나온다.
If you haven't done any Kubernetes deployment, no worries. I have a full course on installing
쿠버네티스 배포를 해본 적이 없더라도 걱정하지 않아도 된다. 설치에 대한 전체 과정이 있습니다.
Kubernetes on CentOS. I provide great detail information including the scripts so you can set
CentOS에서 쿠버네티스 설치. 스크립트를 포함한 훌륭한 세부 정보를 제공하므로 설정할 수 있습니다.
your cluster up quickly if you follow that course.
이 과정을 따라하면 클러스터를 빠르게 설정할 수 있습니다.
So Calico uses a dynamic subnet allocation scheme. It basically uses the Kubernetes API
따라서 캘리코는 동적 서브넷 할당 체계를 사용합니다. 기본적으로 쿠버네티스 API를 사용한다.
server HCD or set up its own HCD if you want to do that that way. So that basically provides,
서버 HCD를 사용하거나 원하는 경우 자체 HCD를 설정할 수 있습니다. 따라서 기본적으로 제공됩니다,
has the reference of what APIs will need to assign to each node. And once Calico is installed,
에는 각 노드에 할당해야 할 API에 대한 참조가 있습니다. 그리고 Calico가 설치되면
then it assigns a block of those IPs to each node and each node is become then responsible
이 되면 각 노드에 해당 IP 블록을 할당하고 각 노드는 그 다음부터
for assigning the IPs to the pods that it creates inside it. The default encapsulation for Calico
내부에 생성하는 파드에 IP를 할당한다. 캘리코의 기본 캡슐화
is IP and IP protocol which basically involves wrapping a layer 3 IP packet inside an extra
는 기본적으로 레이어 3 IP 패킷을 여분의
IP header. Let's see how that kind of really works. So this is an Ethernet frame which consists of
IP 헤더로 감싸는 것입니다. 실제로 어떻게 작동하는지 살펴봅시다. 이더넷 프레임은 다음과 같이 구성됩니다.
the MAC information, the MAC header and the data and the CRC checksum. So these are kind of routine.
MAC 정보, MAC 헤더, 데이터, CRC 체크섬으로 구성되어 있습니다. 따라서 이것들은 일종의 루틴입니다.
It has a MAC address of the server, the originating server and this is the MAC
서버의 MAC 주소, 발신 서버, 그리고 이것이 바로 MAC입니다.
address of the destination server. And then inside that it creates a kind of other shell,
대상 서버의 주소입니다. 그리고 그 안에 일종의 다른 셸을 생성합니다,
an other layer of IP header which really doesn't have anything in it except if we wrap
실제로는 아무것도 들어 있지 않은 다른 계층의 IP 헤더입니다.
the actual data which is again is an IP data. It has an IP source IP, destination IP. So these
실제 데이터는 다시 IP 데이터입니다. 여기에는 소스 IP, 목적지 IP가 있습니다. 따라서 이
are the source and IP address of the pod. So we're talking about pods here and that's how
는 파드의 소스 및 IP 주소입니다. 여기서 우리는 파드에 대해 이야기하고 있으며, 다음과 같이
it knows how to, so basically kind of this information piggybacks on the other layer IP
어떻게 하는지 알고 있기 때문에 기본적으로 이 정보는 다른 레이어 IP에 피기백됩니다.
which has the IP address of the destination server pod. The destination node that has the pod that
대상 서버 파드의 IP 주소가 있다. 파드가 있는 대상 노드는
we are reaching to. So again you're talking about calling one pod from one server to another pod on
를 가진 대상 노드이다. 다시 말해서, 한 서버에서 다른 서버의 파드로 한 파드를 호출하는 것은
a different server. If you are if your pods are communicating on the same server we don't need
다른 서버로 호출하는 것이다. 만약 파드가 동일한 서버에서 통신하고 있다면, 우리는 필요하지 않다.
that. This really only is used by default again. This scheme is used when you're communicating
가 필요하지 않다. 이것은 실제로 다시 기본적으로만 사용된다. 이 체계는 통신할 때 사용된다.
across nodes. So once this packet then is sent it knows how to send that. It has everything that
노드 간에 통신할 때 사용됩니다. 따라서 이 패킷이 전송되면 노드는 이 패킷을 전송하는 방법을 알고 있습니다. 이 패킷에는
needs the MAC addresses, the IP addresses of the servers and then once this frame gets to the
이 프레임이 서버의 MAC 주소와 IP 주소가 필요하고, 일단 이 프레임이
destination server it unpacks it and then it knows where this to which pod it needs to be sending.
대상 서버에 도착하면 압축을 풀고 이 프레임을 어느 파드로 보내야 하는지 알 수 있습니다.
So kind of hide this information, piggybacks it inside another IP header.
따라서 이 정보를 숨기고 다른 IP 헤더 안에 피기백합니다.
And finally Calico uses a border protocol gateway or BGP to share and exchange
마지막으로 Calico는 보더 프로토콜 게이트웨이 또는 BGP를 사용하여 공유 및 교환합니다.
ROPs info between nodes and that that's how it facilitates pod network communication.
ROP는 노드 간 정보를 교환하여 파드 네트워크 통신을 용이하게 합니다.
To demo and explore how Calico works on a Kubernetes environment I'll set up two servers.
칼리코가 쿠버네티스 환경에서 어떻게 작동하는지 데모하고 살펴보기 위해 두 대의 서버를 설정해 보겠습니다.
So I have a Kubernetes cluster. It has two nodes, the master node and node one. And I have pre-installed
Kubernetes 클러스터가 있습니다. 여기에는 마스터 노드와 노드 1이라는 두 개의 노드가 있습니다. 그리고 미리 설치한
a very simple hello world application. It's got four pods as you can see there are two on each node.
아주 간단한 헬로월드 애플리케이션을 사전 설치했습니다. 보시다시피 각 노드에 두 개씩 총 4개의 파드가 있습니다.
And as you can see when CNI actually installs or configures the pod network it also
그리고 CNI가 실제로 파드 네트워크를 설치하거나 구성할 때 볼 수 있듯이
creates the VET part. So it comes in pair. One pair is installed, one part of the pair is installed
VET 파트를 생성한다. 따라서 쌍으로 제공된다. 한 쌍이 설치되고, 한 쌍의 일부가 설치된다.
on the Kubernetes itself, on the pod itself and then the other part the other part of the
쿠버네티스 자체에, 파드 자체에 설치되고, 다른 한 부분은
VET is actually installed on the server so on the host. So as you can see all of these four pods
VET는 실제로 서버에 설치되므로 호스트에 설치됩니다. 보시다시피 이 네 개의 파드는 모두
have four interfaces of IP addresses and each one of those you can see the IP addresses.
에는 네 개의 IP 주소 인터페이스가 있으며 각 인터페이스에서 IP 주소를 볼 수 있습니다.
And also each VET has its counterpart on the server. So next we'll go to the command line
또한 각 VET는 서버에 대응하는 서버가 있습니다. 이제 명령줄로 이동해 보겠습니다.
and kind of explore what this is not a full story of course. Calico has done a lot more and we are
를 실행하고, 물론 이것이 전체 이야기는 아닙니다. Calico는 훨씬 더 많은 일을 해왔고 우리는
going to explore other features of Calico. So I'll be using Visual Studio Code and so we are
Calico의 다른 기능들을 살펴볼 것입니다. 비주얼 스튜디오 코드를 사용할 예정이니까요.
inside Visual Studio Code and I'm already SSH into node one. So as you saw in the previous diagram
에 있고 이미 1번 노드에 SSH로 접속했습니다. 이전 다이어그램에서 보셨듯이
we have two nodes one is master and the other one node one. So I'm running everything from node
두 개의 노드가 있는데 하나는 마스터 노드이고 다른 하나는 1번 노드입니다. 그래서 저는 노드 1에서 모든 것을 실행하고 있습니다.
one. So let's run the first command ip addr or give me all the interfaces on this basically that
하나. 이제 첫 번째 명령인 ip addr을 실행하거나 기본적으로 다음과 같은 모든 인터페이스를 제공하겠습니다.
what it says give me all the interfaces on this machine. So as you can see quite a number of them
이 명령은 이 컴퓨터의 모든 인터페이스를 알려준다는 뜻입니다. 보시다시피 꽤 많은 수의 인터페이스가 있습니다.
it's got a loopback at zero so that is the default interface for the server itself.
루프백이 0으로 설정되어 있으므로 서버 자체의 기본 인터페이스입니다.
And then we see a number of other ones such as Vibro and Docker they're not being used
그리고 사용되지 않는 Vibro 및 Docker와 같은 다른 여러 인터페이스도 볼 수 있습니다.
by Calicker. But Calicker has a number of entries here one is Calico and this GUI and the other one
Calicker에 의해. 하지만 Calicker는 여기에 여러 항목이 있습니다. 하나는 Calico이고 다른 하나는 이 GUI입니다.
is so that is one one of the virtual Ethernet that we saw in the first diagram that connects
는 첫 번째 다이어그램에서 보았던 가상 이더넷 중 하나로서
the server to the pod and this is the other one. So that on this on node one we have two pods
서버와 파드를 연결하고 이것이 다른 하나이다. 따라서 노드 1에는 두 개의 파드가 있다.
each one of those has an interface that connects it to the pod. There's also tunnel zero
각각의 파드에는 파드에 연결하는 인터페이스가 있습니다. 터널 0도 있습니다.
and it's got an ip address. By the way these are these don't have any ip addresses because
그리고 IP 주소가 있습니다. 그런데 이것들은 다음과 같은 이유로 IP 주소가 없습니다.
those are just basically these are the pipeline that connect to servers to connect the server to
이것들은 기본적으로 서버에 연결하기 위해 서버에 연결하는 파이프라인입니다.
the pod. However we also have what is called a tunnel and as you can see is something to do
파드입니다. 그러나 터널이라는 것도 있는데, 보시다시피 터널은
with ip ip. We'll discuss that later but keep in mind that this Calico also creates this interface
와 관련이 있습니다. 이에 대해서는 나중에 설명하겠지만, 이 Calico는 다음과 같은 인터페이스도 생성한다는 점을 기억하세요.
called tunnel zero and it has an ip address. Okay so that's as far as
터널 제로라고 불리는 인터페이스를 생성하며, 이 인터페이스에는 IP 주소가 있습니다. 자, 여기까지입니다.
interface is concerned. Now the next command ip link show type vet. So I'm just going to verify
인터페이스에 관한 것입니다. 이제 다음 명령은 ip link show type vet입니다. 이제 다음을 확인하겠습니다.
again to see how many virtual Ethernet interfaces created. And again no surprise we have two of them
를 다시 입력하여 얼마나 많은 가상 이더넷 인터페이스가 생성되었는지 확인합니다. 역시 놀랍지 않게도 두 개가 있습니다.
is are the one that we show up here so they're kind of verifying that we have the same one
여기에 표시된 것과 동일한 인터페이스가 있다는 것을 확인합니다.
showing up when we run that command. Okay and we can also do ip link show type ip ip so we want
이 명령을 실행할 때 표시됩니다. 좋아, 그리고 우리는 또한 ip link show type ip를 할 수 있습니다.
to verify this guy. We can also do that independently so if you run that we'll see that
를 확인합니다. 독립적으로 실행할 수도 있으므로 이 명령을 실행하면 다음과 같이 표시됩니다.
we'll see that it shows as a tunnel zero and then ip ip.
터널 0으로 표시된 다음 IP로 표시되는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
So this is as far as the the the tunnel that we'll discuss a little bit later and the vet for
여기까지가 우리가 잠시 후에 논의할 터널에 대한 설명이며
for our pods. Now let's do a kubectl get pods minus o y they want just kind of display
를 찾았습니다. 이제 쿠벡툴이 파드를 빼고 디스플레이만 표시하도록 해보자.
all the pods that we have. And again this is very similar to what I'll show you in that
우리가 가지고 있는 모든 파드를 출력한다. 그리고 이것은 다시 내가 보여줄 것과 매우 유사하다.
diagram before page before. So there are four pods that I installed as part of one
다이어그램과 유사합니다. 그래서 제가 하나의 일부로 설치한 4개의 파드가 있습니다.
hello world application. As you can see two of them are running on node one and the other two
헬로 월드 애플리케이션. 보시다시피, 그 중 두 개는 1번 노드에서, 나머지 두 개는 2번 노드에서 실행되고 있습니다.
are running on master. Okay so far so good. Now let's see how to get to one of those so ip
은 마스터에서 실행 중입니다. 지금까지는 괜찮습니다. 이제 그 중 하나에 도달하는 방법을 살펴봅시다.
route get and the ip address. So basically I'm saying I want to go to this pod 172.16.4.94.5
경로 가져 오기와 IP 주소. 기본적으로 저는 이 포드 172.16.4.94.5로 가고 싶다고 말합니다.
that is this guy. So if I want to go from node one where I am I want to go to that
이 사람이에요. 따라서 내가 있는 1번 노드에서 저 노드로 이동하려면
hit that pod. What are the routes that I need to go through? And this is the results which tells me
그 포드를 누르세요. 어떤 경로를 거쳐야 할까요? 결과는 다음과 같습니다.
in order to go hit that pod from the server itself from the node itself you have to go through that
노드 자체에서 서버 자체에서 해당 파드를 공격하려면 다음을 거쳐야 한다.
interface. Again this is the interface of the vet that connects the server to the pod.
인터페이스를 통과해야 한다. 다시 말하지만 이것은 서버와 파드를 연결하는 베트의 인터페이스이다.
So again that's what we show up here this guy here. So in order for any communication that
그래서 다시 여기에 이 사람이 나타납니다. 따라서 모든 통신을 위해서는
hits that pod will need to go through that interface. If we do the same thing for
해당 파드에 도달하려면 해당 인터페이스를 통과해야 합니다. 만약 우리가
the next pod 06 this guy here around that. Again very similarly in order to go from
다음 포드 06이 그 주위에 있습니다. 다시 매우 유사하게
pod one I'm sorry from node one hit that pod we need to go to this interface again that we saw
노드 1에서 미안하지만 그 파드에 도달하려면 다시 이 인터페이스로 이동해야 합니다.
earlier. So there are no bridges here. Every time that you install a pod and install a pod is
를 보았습니다. 그래서 여기에는 브리지가 없다. 파드를 설치하고 파드를 설치할 때마다
installed on a server Calico creates a route for it. Now let's say we want to hit
서버에 설치될 때마다 캘리코가 경로를 생성한다. 이제 우리가
a different pod this one or six is actually on a different server on master.
이 1~6번 파드는 실제로 마스터의 다른 서버에 있습니다.
So how do we get there? So we run that we'll see that in order to hit 206 we need to go
그럼 어떻게 해야 할까? 실행해보면 206에 도달하려면 다음과 같이 해야 한다는 것을 알 수 있다.
through the ip of my92.168.40 that is master so it's on the other server. However we need to go
마스터인 my92.168.40의 IP를 통해 다른 서버에 접속해야 합니다. 하지만 다음과 같이 해야 합니다.
through the tunnel zero and with the ip that is 172.16.94.0 and that was the tunnel that we saw up
터널 0을 통해 172.16.94.0의 IP로 터널을 통과해야 하며, 이것이 우리가 본 터널인
here. So we need to go through that. So that tunnel does the magic. So that tunnel basically
여기요. 그래서 우리는 그것을 통과해야 합니다. 저 터널이 마법을 부립니다. 저 터널은 기본적으로
facilitates the communication between pods on one server and pods on the other server.
한 서버의 파드와 다른 서버의 파드 간의 통신을 용이하게 한다.
Now let's next we'll kind of show you graphically what we discovered from this demo right now.
이제 이 데모에서 발견한 것을 지금 바로 그래픽으로 보여드리겠습니다.
So here's a view of our environment again. We have two servers and then the four pods that we
우리 환경을 다시 한 번 살펴보겠습니다. 두 개의 서버와 네 개의 파드가 있습니다.
saw earlier. And as we saw any communication that on the same server goes to any of these pods
네 개의 파드가 있습니다. 그리고 동일한 서버에서 이 파드 중 어느 한 곳으로 통신이 가는 것을 보았듯이
it has to go through the vet piece on the server side. So again these are connected together. The
서버 측에 있는 검증 부분을 거쳐야 합니다. 그래서 이것들은 다시 서로 연결되어 있습니다. 그리고
interface on the pod is really a kind of one side of the same pair. So you have a pair here and pair
인터페이스는 실제로 같은 쌍의 한 쪽입니다. 따라서 여기에 한 쌍이 있고
and that's how you connect it. So all communication on from the same server going to the pod goes
이렇게 연결하면 됩니다. 따라서 동일한 서버에서 파드로 가는 모든 통신은 다음과 같이 진행됩니다.
through these interfaces. It doesn't matter where they are. However if this one pod wants to
이 인터페이스를 통해 이루어집니다. 어디에 있는지는 중요하지 않습니다. 그러나 이 하나의 파드가
communicate to with another pod on a different server then as we saw it has to go through the
다른 서버의 다른 파드와 통신하려면 앞서 살펴본 것처럼
tunnel. And the tunnel this is where the ip in ip transformation occurs. That is it sticks it
터널을 통과해야 한다. 그리고 이 터널이 바로 아이피 인 아이피 변환이 일어나는 곳입니다. 바로 여기에
creates a an ip header and then encapsulate everything and the ip part of this communication
IP 헤더를 생성한 다음 이 통신의 모든 것과 IP 부분을 캡슐화합니다.
inside that ip. And then it uses its ip address as a source so it kind of masquerades this ip address
를 캡슐화합니다. 그런 다음 해당 IP 주소를 소스로 사용하여 이 IP 주소를 가장합니다.
and then sends it through this interface of the node and then it goes
그런 다음 이 노드의 인터페이스를 통해 전송한 다음
to the other node and then over here it disassembles this that ip information
다른 노드로 보낸 다음 이쪽에서 이 IP 정보를 분해합니다.
and unpacks everything and then sends the information directly to that pod. And so this
모든 압축을 풀고 그 정보를 해당 파드로 직접 보냅니다. 그래서 이
is kind of overview. Next we are going to kind of explore what happens as information that stands
는 일종의 개요입니다. 다음에는 이 정보가 어떤 식으로 저장되는지 살펴보겠습니다.
between you and how ip in ip and the whole encapsulation works. We'll do that next.
사이에 어떤 일이 일어나는지, 그리고 아이피 인 아이피와 전체 캡슐화가 어떻게 작동하는지 살펴보겠습니다. 이 부분은 다음에 하도록 하겠습니다.
In this part of the demo we are going to capture some network traffic and see how ip in ip works
데모의 이 부분에서는 일부 네트워크 트래픽을 캡처하여 ip in ip가 어떻게 작동하는지 살펴보겠습니다.
in action. So first thing let's just run this command kubectl get services to see what
실제로 작동합니다. 먼저, 이 명령어를 실행하여 kubectl get services를 실행하고
get services to see what services we have available for use. And I have this hello world
get services를 실행하여 사용 가능한 서비스를 확인한다. 그리고 이 헬로 월드가 있다.
that we are going to use for this demo. It's a very simple application as you can see the type
이 데모에 사용할 것입니다. 유형에서 볼 수 있듯이 매우 간단한 애플리케이션입니다.
is node port that is we cannot we can actually get to that service from outside the cluster.
은 클러스터 외부에서 실제로 해당 서비스에 접속할 수 없는 노드 포트입니다.
That is the cluster ip and this is the node port port number. So if we do curl http and using
이것이 클러스터 IP이고 이것이 노드 포트 포트 번호입니다. 따라서 http를 curl하고 다음을 사용하여
the ip address of one of the services and the node port ip then we will be able to call the service.
서비스 중 하나의 IP 주소와 노드 포트 IP를 사용하면 서비스를 호출할 수 있습니다.
And we can see the result hello world version number and host name. So very simple
그리고 헬로 월드 버전 번호와 호스트 이름을 확인할 수 있습니다. 매우 간단합니다.
application indeed. So let's again take a look at the pods that we have.
애플리케이션입니다. 이제 우리가 가지고 있는 파드를 다시 살펴봅시다.
And as you recall we have four pods two on each node and these are pod names
기억하시겠지만, 각 노드에 2개씩 4개의 파드가 있으며, 파드 이름은 다음과 같습니다.
the ip addresses are here and those are the nodes. So we have four different pods two on each node.
IP 주소는 여기, 노드는 여기입니다. 따라서 각 노드에 2개씩 4개의 서로 다른 파드가 있습니다.
So let's then we're going to access into one of the nodes so sorry pods so we're going to
이제 노드 중 하나에 접속해서 미안하지만 파드에 접속해 보겠습니다.
access to this guy let's do that and then from here we're going to
이 사람에 대한 액세스를 하고 여기서부터 우리는
call a service on the other node. So one pod on one node is going to make a service call
다른 노드에 있는 서비스를 호출합니다. 따라서 한 노드에 있는 하나의 파드가 서비스 호출을 할 것이다.
to a different pod on a different server. So we're going across the server and to see what's
서비스 호출을 할 것이다. 그래서 우리는 서버를 가로질러서 무엇이 있는지 확인한다.
what's happening. So before running the that curl command let's go ahead and start our capture.
무슨 일이 일어나고 있는지. 따라서 해당 curl 명령을 실행하기 전에 먼저 캡처를 시작하겠습니다.
So I'm using t shark this is the command line version of wireshark so t shark minus i
와이어샤크의 명령줄 버전인 t shark를 사용하고 있으므로 t shark에서 i를 빼고
that is what interface we're going to listen on at zero that is the interface the default interface
이것이 우리가 0에서 수신할 인터페이스이며, 기본 인터페이스인
on node one so we're running from node one minus v means make it verbose print all information
노드 1에서 실행하므로 노드 1에서 v를 빼면 모든 정보를 장황하게 인쇄합니다.
minus y http we are telling wireshark we are interested in http so please listen for http
마이너스 Y HTTP 우리는 와이어샤크에게 HTTP에 관심이 있으니 HTTP를 들어보라고 말하고 있습니다.
traffic so the next thing about wireshark t shark is the understand http so let's run that
트래픽이 있으므로 와이어샤크 티샤크의 다음 작업은 http 이해이므로 실행해 보겠습니다.
so that is ready for us so over here we're going to run that command and that curl and again you
이제 준비가 되었으니 여기에 해당 명령과 컬을 실행하고 다시 한 번
can see the results coming back exactly the same way and over here we'll see that it captures a lot
결과가 정확히 같은 방식으로 돌아오는 것을 볼 수 있으며 여기에서는 많은 것을 캡처하는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
of stuff so let's scroll up here and see what's going on so the capture started from here the
따라서 여기를 위로 스크롤하여 무슨 일이 일어나고 있는지 확인하여 여기에서 캡처를 시작하여
first part is the frame so as you can if you recall the the frame the internet frame contains
첫 번째 부분은 프레임이므로 인터넷 프레임에 포함 된 프레임을 기억할 수 있습니다.
everything so that's the kind of exterior that kind of other part of the whole traffic then
모든 것이 전체 트래픽의 다른 부분과 같은 종류의 외부입니다.
inside that we'll see that we have internet protocol ip and then we'll see the the source
그 안에는 인터넷 프로토콜 IP가 있고 그 다음에는 소스가 표시됩니다.
of our server which is we are going from node one which is 192.168.0.41 and the destination
서버의 노드 1번인 192.168.0.41과 목적지인
is 192.168.0.4 so this is the exterior this is the ip header that it creates
은 192.168.0.4이므로 이것이 외부에 생성되는 IP 헤더입니다.
and then puts everything inside so that's the kind of other shell ip and within that we'll
그리고 모든 것을 내부에 넣어서 다른 쉘 IP를 만들고 그 안에
see there is another and as you can see here it says protocol ip ip so the first ip header
또 다른 셸이 있고 여기서 볼 수 있듯이 프로토콜 아이피 아이피라고 표시되어 있으므로 첫 번째 아이피 헤더는
is of the type ip ip protocol and inside that is actually the again the ip header but this is the
는 ip ip 프로토콜 유형이고 그 안에는 실제로 다시 ip 헤더가 있지만 이것은
ip header of actual communication that one pod is trying to send to the other and the source for this
한 파드가 다른 파드로 보내려는 실제 통신의 IP 헤더와 이에 대한 소스이다.
is 172.168.194.0 if you recall that is the ip address of the tunnel so the tunnel on
는 172.168.194.0이며, 이는 터널의 IP 주소이므로 터널의
node one is actually masquerading the ip address of the the pod itself so
노드 1은 실제로는 파드 자체의 IP 주소를 가장하고 있기 때문에
our and then the destination is 206 so this is the the service that we are going we're calling
그리고 목적지는 206이므로 우리가 호출하는 서비스는 다음과 같다.
on one and one is to 168.60 so again that's the ip address the destination ip address
하나는 168.60으로 연결되므로 다시 한 번 목적지 IP 주소입니다.
and within that we'll see that let's just scroll down this is the the tcp part as you know http is
그리고 그 안에서 아래로 스크롤을 내리면 여러분이 알고있는 것처럼 이것이 http 부분이라는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
tcp basically and then the destination port is 8080 that's exactly what we are calling
기본적으로 tcp이고 대상 포트는 정확히 우리가 호출하는 8080입니다.
and then there are some handshake going on here and then a little bit later it starts packing
그리고 여기서 핸드셰이크가 진행되고 잠시 후 패킹이 시작됩니다.
and kind of getting everything together and it starts creating the the ethernet so this is going
그리고 모든 것을 모아서 이더넷을 생성하기 시작합니다.
reverse now we're going from the the master that's what the service was on the service
반대로 이제 우리는 서비스에서 서비스가 있던 마스터에서 가고 있습니다.
starts responding and starts creating the ethernet so that's the ethernet frame
응답을 시작하고 이더넷을 생성하기 시작하여 이더넷 프레임이 됩니다.
and then inside that again it creates another ethernet
그리고 그 안에 또 다른 이더넷을 생성합니다.
frame header again the destination now is reversed the source would be 40 we're going from
프레임 헤더가 다시 목적지가 뒤바뀌고 소스는 40이 됩니다.
the second server back to our server where we started everything else and then you can see
두 번째 서버는 다른 모든 것을 시작한 서버로 돌아가서 다음을 볼 수 있습니다.
it's exactly the same as it kind of reverse fast packet packets everything all the information and
모든 정보를 역방향으로 빠른 패킷으로 전송하는 것과 똑같습니다.
sends it back to the to the server to the caller to the pod that was calling it and this is the
를 호출한 파드의 호출자에게 서버로 다시 전송하고, 이것이 바로
the package the information that is sending it back again is exactly a hello world version so
다시 보내는 패키지의 정보는 정확히 헬로 월드 버전이므로
this is how ip in ip happens it's kind of like magic is very simple and very powerful
이것이 IP에서 IP가 발생하는 방식입니다. 마술은 매우 간단하면서도 매우 강력합니다.
especially if servers are on different like they're not maybe a different subnet so that
특히 서버가 다른 서브넷에 있는 것처럼 다른 서버에 있는 경우, 그래서
makes it things very easy to to manage so this that is the demo for the default when we install
을 사용하면 관리가 매우 쉬워지므로 설치 시 기본값으로 제공되는 데모는 다음과 같습니다.
calico and we use its default ip in ip encapsulation so hopefully by now you have
옥양목 그리고 우리는 IP 캡슐화에서 기본 IP를 사용하므로 지금 쯤이면 다음과 같을 것입니다.
some understanding of how cni providers work and also you have some understanding of understanding
CNI 공급자가 어떻게 작동하는지에 대해 어느 정도 이해하셨을 것입니다.
of how calico using the default settings work but there is a lot more into calico
기본 설정을 사용하는 옥양목의 작동 방식에 대한 이해가 있지만 옥양목에는 훨씬 더 많은 것이 있습니다.
and we don't have to discuss everything in this session but i'm going to talk about a couple of
이 세션에서 모든 것을 논의할 필요는 없지만 몇 가지에 대해 이야기하겠습니다.
things here first we will just explore how calico shares route information amongst its nodes and
먼저 캘리코가 노드들 간에 경로 정보를 공유하는 방법과
you're going to talk about the protocol called border gateway protocol or bgp and that is
보더 게이트웨이 프로토콜 또는 BGP라는 프로토콜에 대해 이야기 할 것입니다.
something that calico leverages in order for it to share routing information between nodes
캘리코가 노드 간 라우팅 정보를 공유하기 위해 활용하는 프로토콜입니다.
and then following that we will discuss non-ip and ip routing so ip and ip is the default mode
그 다음에는 비-IP 및 IP 라우팅에 대해 설명할 것이므로 기본 모드는 IP 및 IP입니다.
and that is something that we kind of all examples up to this point have been using ip and ip so if
지금까지의 모든 예제들이 ip와 ip를 사용했기 때문에 만약
you don't make any changes into calico settings when you install it by default it uses ip and ip
설치 시 캘리코 설정을 변경하지 않으면 기본적으로 IP와 IP를 사용합니다.
it has some over overhead but it's not much but still there is an overhead so if there are
약간의 오버 헤드가 있지만 그다지 많지는 않지만 여전히 오버 헤드가 있으므로 다음과 같은 경우
situations that you don't really need ip and ip and we go through some of those situations it's better
IP와 IP가 실제로 필요하지 않은 상황이 있고 그러한 상황을 겪는 것이 더 좋습니다.
to actually not use any encapsulation that makes it actually faster and we call it direct there's
실제로 더 빠르게 만드는 캡슐화를 사용하지 않고 직접 호출하는 것이 더 낫습니다.
also another option for bxlan if there is there are situations which you can use direct communication
또한 직접 통신을 사용할 수 있는 상황이 있는 경우 bxlan의 또 다른 옵션이 있습니다.
or you can't use ip and ip routing then bxlan is another option it's kind of similar to
또는 IP 및 IP 라우팅을 사용할 수 없는 경우 bxlan은 다음과 유사한 또 다른 옵션입니다.
flannel that we've discussed in the previous presentation
이전 프레젠테이션에서 설명한 플란넬을 사용합니다.
bgp is a standardized exterior gateway protocol which is designed to exchange routing and
bgp는 라우팅을 교환하도록 설계된 표준화된 외부 게이트웨이 프로토콜입니다.
reachability information among autonomous systems on the internet so internet is really is run by
인터넷의 자율 시스템 간의 도달 가능성 정보를 교환하도록 설계된 표준 외부 게이트웨이 프로토콜입니다.
bgp bgp has really two functions kind of overview one is who on the internet i can send packet to
인터넷에서 누구에게 패킷을 보낼 수 있는지를 알려주는 두 가지 기능이 있다.
i in this case means a router so rather then we'll know how who on the internet i can send
이 경우 i는 라우터를 의미하므로 인터넷에서 누구에게 보낼 수 있는지 알 수 있습니다.
the packet to and the second is make a decision which route should the packet take so let's kind
패킷을 보내고 두 번째는 패킷이 어떤 경로로 갈지 결정하는 것입니다.
so let's kind of this is very general overview of what bgp is obviously in depth this is very
그래서 이것은 BGP가 분명히 깊이 있는 것에 대한 매우 일반적인 개요입니다.
complicated system but just for our understanding in the context of kubernetes and calico so let's
복잡한 시스템이지만 쿠버네티스와 캘리코의 맥락에서 우리의 이해를 돕기 위해
say we have there are four networks that they are not connected together yet through bgp and each
네 개의 네트워크가 있는데 아직 bgp를 통해 서로 연결되어 있지 않고 각각
network only knows about its own route so a only knows about a co only knows about c and so on
네트워크는 자신의 경로에 대해서만 알고 있으므로 A는 A에 대해서만 알고 있고, B는 B에 대해서만 알고 있고, C는 C에 대해서만 알고 있습니다.
and let's say administrators in these two networks configure their systems to then communicate with
이 두 네트워크의 관리자가 다음 네트워크와 통신하도록 시스템을 구성한다고 가정해 보겠습니다.
each other as far as through bgp and as you can see then b update is routing information because
를 통해 서로 통신하도록 구성했다고 가정하면, 보시다시피 B 업데이트는 라우팅 정보입니다.
by just connecting to the a it knows that the how to get to network a and there's only
A에 연결하기만 하면 A 네트워크에 도달하는 방법을 알 수 있습니다.
one route between itself and a same thing a knows about b now that they kind of handshake
자신과 A 사이에 하나의 경로가 있다는 것을 A가 B에 대해 알고 있기 때문에 이제 그들은 일종의 악수를 합니다.
they have a handshake here and so then let's say a and c are connected set up to communicate each
여기서 핸드셰이크를 한 다음 A와 C가 각각 통신하도록 설정된 상태로 연결되어 있다고 가정해 봅시다.
other through bgp the same thing here c knows about a and the number of hops is one and again
다른 하나는 bgp를 통해 c가 a에 대해 알고 있고 홉 수는 하나이고 다시 한 번
same thing between c and d and now again and so on so now we have these four networks that
C와 D 사이에서도 마찬가지입니다. 이제 우리는 다음과 같은 네 개의 네트워크를 갖게 되었습니다.
know a little bit about each other but periodically they also exchange information for
서로에 대해 조금 알고 있지만 주기적으로 정보를 교환합니다.
instance network a can enforce share information with network b and tells b these are the routes
인스턴스 네트워크 A는 네트워크 B와 정보 공유를 강제할 수 있으며, B에게 다음 경로를 알려줍니다.
that i know about so when it does that then network b take a look say hey interesting
내가 알고 있는 정보이므로 네트워크 B는 이걸 보고 흥미롭다고 말합니다.
well of course i know about myself and i already connected with you so i know about you but i did
물론 나는 나 자신에 대해 알고 있고 이미 당신과 연결되어 있으므로 당신에 대해 알고 있습니다.
not know how to get to c now i know so it updates its routing table here and now it has it knows how
이제 C에가는 방법을 모르기 때문에 여기에서 라우팅 테이블을 업데이트하고 이제 방법을 알고 있습니다.
to get c to see so in order to get to see it has to go through a so and the number of hops is two
C로 가기 위해서는 A를 거쳐야 하고 홉 수는 두 개입니다.
so b to c goes to a and then c and b also shares the same information with d and then d also now
따라서 B에서 C로 이동한 다음 C와 B도 D와 동일한 정보를 공유하고 이제 D도 동일한 정보를 공유합니다.
updates its information at now d knows how to get to a it knows it needs to go through b and
정보를 업데이트합니다. 이제 D는 A에 도달하는 방법을 알고 있으며 B를 거쳐야 한다는 것을 알고 있습니다.
it's the number of hops is two and finally after all this handshake is done then every
홉의 수는 두 개이고 마지막으로 이 모든 핸드셰이크가 완료된 후 모든
kind of network knows about at least how to get to other networks so this is the essence of how
종류의 네트워크는 적어도 다른 네트워크에 도달하는 방법을 알고 있으므로 이것이 바로 어떻게
bgp works and calico takes advantage of this protocol in order to share routes among its nodes
BGP가 작동하고 캘리코는 이 프로토콜을 활용하여 노드 간에 경로를 공유합니다.
now let's see how calico actually leverages bgp when we install calico by default it creates a
이제 캘리코를 설치할 때 기본적으로 캘리코가 어떻게 bgp를 활용하는지 살펴보자.
full measure of internal bgp connections and that way it does it every it peers every node with
내부 bgp 연결의 전체 측정값을 생성하고 모든 노드를 피어링할 때 마다
every other node and that's how we have a full mesh so any rod change rod changes happening on
다른 모든 노드를 피어링하는 방식으로 전체 메시를 가지므로 모든 로드 변경 로드 변경은
one node that is reflected immediately in every other node so they will be aware of that if we
한 노드에서 발생하는 로드 변경은 다른 모든 노드에 즉시 반영되므로, 다른 노드에서 이를 인지할 수 있습니다.
have a l2 network that is if we have all our network on the same sub and we have all our
모든 네트워크가 동일한 서브에 있고 우리의 모든
servers kubernetes endpoints notes on the same subnet then calico can leverage l2
서버 쿠버네티스 엔드포인트 노트가 동일한 서브넷에 있다면 캘리코는 L2를 활용할 수 있다.
otherwise if we have maybe some of our servers on a different node on a different subnet then we can
그렇지 않으면 다른 서브넷의 다른 노드에 서버 중 일부가 있다면
configure to use ip and ip instead as long as ip and ip traffic is not blocked then full
IP 및 IP 트래픽이 차단되지 않는 한 대신 IP 및 IP를 사용하도록 구성합니다.
range can be established using layer 3 network note that if we choose to use bxlan instead
레이어 3 네트워크를 사용하여 범위를 설정할 수 있습니다. 대신 bxlan을 사용하도록 선택하면 다음과 같습니다.
that is not bhp is not supported in that scenario now let's say we have a kubernetes cluster we have
이 시나리오에서는 bhp가 지원되지 않습니다. 이제 우리가 가지고 있는 쿠버네티스 클러스터가 있다고 가정해 보겠습니다.
four nodes as you can see here the next step for us would be to install calico and that is how we
여기서 볼 수 있듯이 네 개의 노드가 있다. 다음 단계는 캘리코를 설치하는 것이고, 이렇게 하면 된다.
install calico when we run that calico starts installing some software and kind of in
캘리코를 실행하면 캘리코가 일부 소프트웨어를 설치하기 시작합니다.
can think of it as installing a virtual router on each of the node and then that becomes really
각 노드에 가상 라우터를 설치하는 것으로 생각할 수 있으며, 그러면 실제로는
each node becomes an independent network and then establishes full mesh that is every node is paired
각 노드는 독립적인 네트워크가 되고 모든 노드가 쌍을 이루는 풀 메시를 설정합니다.
directly with every other node and that is how the full mesh is realized and this really works great
다른 모든 노드와 직접 연결되어 풀 메시가 실현되는 방식이며 이는 정말 훌륭하게 작동합니다.
and it is really fast if we have maybe not too many kubernetes nodes but if we start adding you
그리고 쿠버네티스 노드가 너무 많지 않다면 정말 빠르지만, 우리가 당신을 추가하기 시작하면
know our networks become bigger and you know demand for network or kubernetes cluster becomes
네트워크가 커지고 네트워크 또는 쿠버네티스 클러스터에 대한 수요가 증가한다는 것을 알고 있다.
bigger maybe we add a lot more nodes and as you can see in the long run this kind of full mesh
더 커지면 더 많은 노드를 추가할 수 있고, 장기적으로는 이런 종류의 풀 메시가 필요할 수도 있습니다.
is not going to work out so fortunately calico supports raw reflectors basically what it means
는 작동하지 않을 것이므로 다행히도 캘리코는 기본적으로 원시 리플렉터를 지원합니다.
is we can select a few number of nodes and then establish full mesh among those nodes and then
는 몇 개의 노드를 선택한 다음 그 노드들 사이에 풀 메시를 설정한 다음
have other nodes appear with those nodes and that if there are then any changes that happens in a
에 다른 노드가 그 노드와 함께 나타나도록 하고, 그 후 어떤 변화가 생기면
sub bgp let's say this node has a number of nodes that are connected to it then any changes in any
서브 BGP 이 노드에 연결된 노드가 여러 개 있다고 가정하면, 이 노드에 연결된 노드 중
of those nodes any rots information it sends to this node a and then that's node a and then it
그 노드들 중 어떤 노드에서 어떤 로트 정보를 이 노드 A로 보내면 노드 A가
also reflects those changes it changes to the nodes that are directly appeared with it inside
또한 내부에 직접 나타나는 노드에 변경된 변경 사항을 반영합니다.
that group and then start doing the same thing with other leaders of the nodes and then over time
해당 그룹의 다른 노드 리더들에게도 동일한 작업을 시작하고 시간이 지남에 따라
those changes are reflected and then every any changes that happens in one node as far as rots
이러한 변경 사항이 반영되고 한 노드에서 발생하는 모든 변경 사항이 로트까지 반영됩니다.
concerned are reflected in other nodes and that really works great in works great in a larger
관련된 다른 노드에 반영되며, 이는 더 큰 노드에서 잘 작동한다.
kubernetes cluster if we set up kubernetes on our premise on our
클러스터에 쿠버네티스를 설치하는 경우 쿠버네티스 클러스터에서
you know cloud maybe internal cloud we have full control we can configure calico to peer directly
클라우드가 내부 클라우드일 수도 있고, 우리가 모든 권한을 가지고 있으며, 캘리코가 직접 피어링하도록 구성할 수 있다.
with our physical network infrastructure what it means really typically we disable calico's full
우리의 물리적 네트워크 인프라를 사용하면 일반적으로 캘리코를 완전히 비활성화합니다.
mesh if a full mesh behavior and instead we peer calico with our lta uh l3 um top of the rack
메시 동작을 비활성화하고 대신 랙 상단의 LTA L3 음으로 캘리코를 피어링합니다.
rather so we have a number of options if you have a small network then we can use full mesh as is
오히려 네트워크가 작은 경우 풀 메시를 그대로 사용할 수 있는 다양한 옵션이 있습니다.
as it grows we can then choose to have rod reflectors and the best option is if you have
네트워크가 커지면 로드 리플렉터를 선택할 수 있으며 가장 좋은 옵션은 다음과 같은 경우입니다.
full control over our environment and we have a hardware that supports off of the rack then we can
환경을 완전히 제어하고 랙에서 벗어난 하드웨어를 지원하는 하드웨어가 있으면 다음을 수행 할 수 있습니다.
actually configure our network to use top of the rack and set up mesh full bgp in that way so in
실제로 랙 상단을 사용하도록 네트워크를 구성하고 그런 방식으로 메쉬 풀 BGP를 설정하여
the previous two slides we saw how bgp works in general and we saw how calico implements bgp as
앞의 두 슬라이드에서 우리는 일반적으로 bgp가 어떻게 작동하는지 보았고, 캘리코가 어떻게 bgp를 구현하는지 보았습니다.
a full mesh by default now let's dig a little bit deeper into what happens actually when we set up
이제 풀 메시를 기본으로 설정했을 때 실제로 어떤 일이 일어나는지 조금 더 자세히 살펴보겠습니다.
calico and what processes are involved and what services are involved let's say we have our cluster
옥양목과 어떤 프로세스가 관련되어 있고 어떤 서비스가 관련되어 있는지 살펴보자.
again we have two servers and consisting of our cluster and we are using isa ip in ip as a default
다시 두 대의 서버가 있고 클러스터를 구성하고 있으며 기본값으로 isa ip in ip를 사용하고 있습니다.
encapsulation method and as you can see each node has its own network namespace has a default
캡슐화 방법을 사용하고 있으며, 보시다시피 각 노드마다 고유한 네트워크 네임스페이스가 기본값인
and then we've got that there with an ip address on each side there's also because you're using ip
그리고 양쪽에 IP 주소가 있는데, 그 이유는 당신이 IP
and ip there's a tunnel that is set up on each node i haven't shown this over here i'm just
그리고 각 노드에 설정된 터널이 있습니다. 여기에는 표시하지 않았습니다.
showing it over here so but there'll be a tunnel over here as well so any communication that
여기에 표시했지만 여기에도 터널이 있으므로 모든 통신은 다음과 같습니다.
happens across the service between services and pods and go across the the node that goes through
서비스와 파드 사이에서 발생하는 모든 통신은 서비스와 파드 사이를 통과하는 노드를 통과한다.
the node it goes through a tunnel let's see what happens when we install a service which has used
터널을 통과하는 노드에 서비스를 설치하면 어떤 일이 발생하는지 살펴보자.
install deploys a single pod so as we saw earlier what happens is the api server calls into cubelet
설치는 단일 파드를 배포하므로 앞서 살펴본 것처럼 API 서버가 큐블렛으로 호출한다.
cubelet calls into cni plugin the plugin creates the pod name or network namespace
cubelet이 CNI 플러그인을 호출하면 플러그인이 파드 이름 또는 네트워크 네임스페이스를 생성한다.
and then it creates the vets that is a virtual ethernet on both sides so we have one side this
그리고 양쪽에 가상 이더넷인 vets를 생성하여 한쪽에는 다음과 같이 만든다.
has an ip address the other side is not it just basically a pipe that connects these two
다른 쪽은 기본적으로 이 둘을 연결하는 파이프가 아닌가요?
and also sets the default route for the new pod next thing that it does it calls into a daemon
그리고 새로운 파드의 기본 경로를 설정하고 다음에 데몬으로 호출한다.
called felix that is installed by calico when we saw calico its primary role is to manage the routes
캘리코가 설치한 펠릭스는 경로를 관리하는 것이 주된 역할이다.
so now that we have a new route it actually programs the route table and it adds the ip
이제 새 경로가 생겼으므로 실제로 경로 테이블을 프로그래밍하고 IP를 추가합니다.
address the destination of this pod and how do we get to that in order to get to that pod because
이 파드의 목적지를 주소로 지정하고 해당 파드에 도달하기 위해 어떻게 해야 하는지 알려준다.
it's on the same server we just simply go through this calico
같은 서버에 있기 때문에 우리는 그냥 이 옥양목을 통과하면 된다.
interface here so that's that's what it does and the next thing that it does it calls the
인터페이스를 호출하여 이 작업을 수행하고 그 다음에는
it calls another a service called bird this is basically a bgp agent and that bgp agent passes
새라는 다른 서비스를 호출합니다. 이것은 기본적으로 BGP 에이전트이고 그 BGP 에이전트는 다음을 전달합니다.
that information the route that just we created it passed through the bgp agent from one node
방금 생성한 경로가 한 노드에서 BGP 에이전트를 통과한 정보입니다.
it talks to the bgp agent or bird on the other node it also then talks to its own felix passes
다른 노드의 BGP 에이전트 또는 버드와 대화한 다음 자체 펠릭스 패스와도 대화합니다.
the information about the new route and then the felix on the second node also program is route
새 경로에 대한 정보를 전달하고 두 번째 노드의 펠릭스도 경로를 프로그램합니다.
table is the destination again is the same however because this is going through across
테이블은 목적지가 다시 동일하지만, 이것은 가로질러 가기 때문에
the nodes you'll see that it goes through the tunnel zero so any communication that
노드에서 터널 0을 통과하는 것을 볼 수 있으므로 모든 통신이
is destined for this ip address for this pod will need to go through tunnel zero so in summary
이 파드의 이 IP 주소로 향하는 모든 통신은 터널 0을 통과해야 하므로 요약하면 다음과 같다.
when you install calico it installs two important um demons one is called felix that manages
캘리코를 설치하면 두 개의 중요한 음 악마가 설치되는데, 하나는 펠릭스라는 이름으로 관리한다.
and programs the route table and then the bird which is the bgp agent and that's how the different
그리고 경로 테이블을 프로그래밍하고 그 다음에는 BGP 에이전트인 새를 프로그래밍합니다.
nodes talk to each other the the bgp agents talk to each other and that's how when and a new rod
노드들이 서로 대화하는 방식입니다. 그래서 언제 그리고 새로운 로드인
is added on one node is reflected on every other node so the last thing i wanted to talk about was
가 한 노드에 추가되면 다른 모든 노드에 반영되므로 마지막으로 이야기하고 싶었던 것은
calico networking options so so far in our sample cluster we had two nodes and we were we have been
옥양목 네트워킹 옵션으로 지금까지 샘플 클러스터에는 두 개의 노드가 있었고, 우리는
using ip and ip overlay network and that may not be the best option in our prim is actually not the
IP 및 IP 오버레이 네트워크를 사용하고 있으며 이는 우리의 프라임에서 최선의 옵션이 아닐 수 있습니다.
good the best option at all so we'll talk about some other options that provide better performance
좋은 옵션이 아니므로 더 나은 성능을 제공하는 다른 옵션에 대해 이야기하겠습니다.
first one is non-overlay network and this is the most performer performant option as there is no
첫 번째는 비 오버레이 네트워크이며 가장 성능이 좋은 옵션입니다.
encapsulation and decapsulation because that will take cpu time in order to do that
캡슐화 및 디캡슐레이션을 수행하는 데 CPU 시간이 걸리기 때문입니다.
we have a couple of options if you have control over our hardware and our hardware supports
하드웨어와 하드웨어 지원을 제어할 수 있는 경우 몇 가지 옵션이 있습니다.
top of rack then you can simply use bgp to peer with top of rack routers and the benefit of this
랙 상단에 있는 경우 BGP를 사용하여 랙 상단에 있는 라우터와 피어링할 수 있으며 다음과 같은 이점이 있습니다.
first of all there is no encapsulation and the second benefit that we get is that our ip
우선 캡슐화가 없고, 두 번째 이점은 우리의 IP가
pod ips will be routable from outside the cluster so that's very nice if that's not possible but we
파드 아이피를 클러스터 외부에서 라우팅할 수 있다는 것인데, 이것이 가능하지 않다면 매우 좋지만
have all our our nodes on the same subnet l2 subnet then we can simply use calico for bgp
모든 노드가 동일한 서브넷 L2 서브넷에 있다면, 우리는 간단히 BGP에 캘리코를 사용할 수 있다.
peering you know among nodes and then basically use it that way in that in that case we will not
노드 간에 피어링을 하고 기본적으로 이 경우엔
we will not be using any encapsulation although we are not those uh pod ips will not be routable
우리는 캡슐화를 사용하지 않을 것이지만, 어, 파드 아이피는 라우팅할 수 없다.
from outside the cluster that's the only disadvantage of that but
클러스터 외부에서 접근하는 것이 유일한 단점이지만
other that other than that it gives you the performance of the first option
그 외에는 첫 번째 옵션의 성능을 제공한다.
if you are in a situation where we have our nodes on multiple subnets then there's another option
여러 서브넷에 노드가 있는 상황이라면 다른 옵션이 있습니다.
called cross subnets overlay and basically the way it works it among the uh it configures in a way
크로스 서브넷 오버레이라고 불리며 기본적으로 다음과 같은 방식으로 구성됩니다.
that for the nodes that are on the same subnets it won't use any encapsulation however if you
동일한 서브넷에 있는 노드에 대해서는 캡슐화를 사용하지 않지만 다음과 같은 경우에는 캡슐화를 사용하지 않습니다.
are crossing going you know one you're calling one pod is calling a service on a different
이 교차하는 경우, 한 파드를 호출하는 파드가 다른 파드의 서비스를 호출하고 있다는 것을 알 수 있다.
node which is on a different subnet then you can configure calico to either use ip and ip
노드가 다른 서브넷에 있다면, 캘리코가 IP와 IP 중 하나를 사용하도록 구성할 수 있다.
or vxlan as we cross the boundary so that's that's really good option to get the best of both worlds
또는 경계를 넘을 때 vxlan을 사용하도록 설정하면 두 가지 장점을 모두 얻을 수 있는 좋은 옵션입니다.
one is um you get the benefit of no overlay we are if you're on the same l2 network and also it
하나는 동일한 L2 네트워크에 있는 경우 오버레이가 없다는 이점을 얻을 수 있습니다.
provides overlay uh if for the situations where we are crossing the subnet and the last one of course
오버레이를 제공합니다 물론 우리가 서브넷과 마지막 서브넷을 교차하는 상황에 대비하여
is using a full overlay network and that's what we've been using up to this point and this is a
는 전체 오버레이 네트워크를 사용하고 있으며 이것이 지금까지 우리가 사용했던 것이고 이것은
situation where in none of this is possible so we can use either ip and ip which i've used for
이 중 어느 것도 가능하지 않은 상황에서 우리는 내가 사용했던 IP와 IP를 사용할 수 있습니다.
this demo or you can use vxlan so that's kind of up to you so this is these are the options as far
이 데모를 사용하거나 vxlan을 사용할 수 있으므로 이는 귀하에게 달려 있으므로 지금까지 옵션은 다음과 같습니다.
as the on-prem is concerned these are very similar if you're running you want to decide if you decide
온-프레미스와 관련하여 실행중인 경우 매우 유사합니다.
to run your cluster on a either azure or google or amazon mostly the same things apply although
there are some differences for instance it's coming to be aware of if you're running in azure
몇 가지 차이점이 있는데, 예를 들어 azure에서 실행하는 경우 알아두어야 할 사항이 있습니다.
for instance azure does not support ip and ip so if you are in a situation which you can't use a
예를 들어 azure는 IP와 IP를 지원하지 않으므로 사용할 수없는 상황에 처한 경우
non-overlay within azure and you have to use overlay then you have to use vxlan
오버레이를 사용할 수 없는 상황이고 오버레이를 사용해야 하는 경우 VXLAN을 사용해야 합니다.
also there are some differences between them so if you are running in in the in the cloud then i
또한 그들 사이에는 약간의 차이가 있으므로 클라우드에서 실행하는 경우 i
encourage you to read the documentation calico documentation i'll provide the link in the
문서를 읽어보시길 권장합니다. 옥양목 문서에 링크를 제공하겠습니다.
description next i'll show you how to make these uh configuration changes obviously ideally
설명 다음에는 이러한 설정을 이상적으로 변경하는 방법을 보여드리겠습니다.
you want to make the decision before you set up your cluster because you don't want to you know
클러스터를 설정하기 전에 결정을 내리고 싶지 않으니까요.
make these fundamental changes as your you have you know clients and your workload running on it
클라이언트와 그 위에서 실행되는 워크로드를 알고 있으므로 이러한 근본적인 변경을 수행한다.
so i'll that i'll show you next so in order to change the network setting calico network setting
그래서 다음에 보여드리겠습니다. 네트워크 설정을 변경하기 위해 옥양목 네트워크 설정을 변경합니다.
after is installed we need to install a command line cfi called calico ctl i'll put a link in the
설치가 완료되면 옥양목 ctl이라는 명령 줄 cfi를 설치해야합니다.
description so you can go you guys can go ahead and install it yourself if you want to interact
설명에 링크를 넣을 테니 상호작용을 원한다면 직접 설치하세요.
with calico and learn more about how it works so the first command we're going to look at the
옥양목과 어떻게 작동하는지 더 자세히 알아보기 위해 첫 번째 명령어는
calico note status so let's run that i'll put in my password
캘리코 노트 상태이므로 비밀번호를 입력해 보겠습니다.
and this shows us the bgps status of our cluster so right now this is the peer address so i'm
그리고 이것은 클러스터의 BGPS 상태를 보여 주므로 지금은 이것이 피어 주소이므로
looking at this is i'm running these commands on the master node and i have only one more node so
이걸 보면 마스터 노드에서 이 명령을 실행 중이고 노드가 하나만 더 있으므로
you'll see that this is the other node so we are looking at what server we're peering with and
이것이 다른 노드임을 알 수 있으므로 어떤 서버를 피어링하고 있는지 살펴보고 있습니다.
that's the other node that is node one and peer type is node to node and is mesh so this is the
이 다른 노드는 노드 1이고 피어 유형은 노드 대 노드이며 메시이므로 이것은
default behavior and status is up which is a good thing and already established so this is how you
기본 동작과 상태는 올라간 상태이며, 이는 좋은 일이고 이미 설정되었으므로 다음과 같습니다.
get the the status of your bgp once you install calico if you want to see if everything is running
모든 것이 실행 중인지 확인하려면 캘리코를 설치한 후 BGP의 상태를 확인합니다.
correctly and the peers are you know um interacting with each other and it's up then just run it
올바르게 그리고 동료들이 서로 상호 작용하고 있다는 것을 알고 있다면 그냥 실행하십시오.
command um pseudo calico node status so in order to make changes to our network setting the
명령으로 가짜 옥양목 노드 상태를 변경하여 네트워크 설정을 변경하기 위해
first we need to look at what's called ip pool so let's run that command and so in calico you can
먼저 IP 풀이라는 것을 살펴볼 필요가 있으므로 해당 명령을 실행하여 옥양목에서 다음과 같이 할 수 있습니다.
have set multiple ip pools by default there's only one so this is the only it is the pool that
기본적으로 여러 개의 IP 풀이 설정되어 있으므로 이것이 유일한 풀입니다.
all the um the pods on all nodes get their ip addresses from so this is the complete
모든 노드의 모든 파드가 IP 주소를 얻으므로 이것이 완전한
ip so it's 172.16.0.0.0-16 so this is where um obviously each node gets its own block so it kind
172.16.0.0.0.0-16이므로 각 노드가 자체 블록을 가져와서
of sub uh creates subnets within this full range of ip's and so everything starts with 172.16
이 전체 IP 범위 내에서 서브넷을 생성하므로 모든 것이 172.16으로 시작됩니다.
and then on one node is i believe 16 on the other dot 94 so about everything starts with 172.16
그리고 한 노드에 16이 있고 다른 노드에 94가 있어서 거의 모든 것이 172.16으로 시작됩니다.
and that's how the uh the the pods get their ip addresses from now we need to actually
그리고 그게 바로 지금부터 파드가 IP 주소를 얻는 방법입니다.
download this uh file so calico ctl get ip pool and this is the name of the file that we need to
이 파일을 다운로드하여 캘리코가 IP 풀을 가져오고 이것이 우리가 필요로하는 파일 이름입니다.
get ip default dash ipv4 pool and then i'm just downloading it downloading inside a yaml file
get ip 기본 대시 IPv4 풀을 다운로드 한 다음 yaml 파일 내에서 다운로드하는 중입니다.
so we can modify that so let's go ahead run that and that's done but we can open that
그래서 우리는 그것을 수정할 수 있으므로 계속해서 실행하고 완료되었지만 그것을 열 수 있습니다.
in nano and take a look at the file and modify that so this is the setting um so let's just go
나노에서 파일을 살펴보고 수정할 수 있으므로 이것이 설정이므로 음, 그냥 가자.
through that quickly again the kind is ip pool ip and then um the create time and so this is a
그것을 통해 다시 빨리 종류는 아이피 풀 아이피 그리고 음 생성 시간 그래서 이것은
meta data information and this is the name of the file i've just opened so and then some information
메타 데이터 정보이고 이것은 방금 열었던 파일의 이름입니다.
so this is the name of the file that i've just opened so and then some information so this is
그래서 이것은 내가 방금 열었던 파일의 이름과 일부 정보이므로 이것은 다음과 같습니다.
the block size it's 26 and the side there as we looked at is 172.16.00 again same information that
블록 크기는 26이고 우리가 보았던 측면은 172.16.00이고 다시 동일한 정보입니다.
we saw and this is the important part so it says ip mode always so this is by default this is if we
우리가 보았고 이것이 중요한 부분이므로 항상 IP 모드라고 표시되므로 기본적으로 이것은 다음과 같은 경우입니다.
just download the yaml file from calico and install calico it by default it says to always
옥양목에서 yaml 파일을 다운로드하고 옥양목을 설치하면 기본적으로 항상 다음과 같이 표시됩니다.
and then um at the at the bottom you'll see that um vxlan mode is never because we are not using
그리고 맨 아래에는 우리가 사용하지 않기 때문에 VXLAN 모드가 아닌
vxlan so let's go ahead and make a change here and let's in order to make calico not to use ip and ip
vxlan을 사용하지 않기 때문이므로 여기서 변경하여 옥양목에 IP와 IP
all we need to do is just make a change here and change this to never oops
우리가 해야 할 일은 여기서 변경을 하고 이것을 never oops로 변경하는 것뿐입니다.
changes to never oops i should be looking where i'm typing
내가 입력하는 곳을 찾아야 합니다.
so like a change here
그래서 여기처럼 변경
never so that's all the change that we need to make and if we remember that if we have if you're
결코 그래서 우리가해야 할 모든 변화와 우리가 그것을 기억한다면 당신이 있다면
in a situation where you have some nodes um on you know on one subnet and others um on the other
어떤 노드는 한 서브넷에 있고 다른 노드는 다른 서브넷에 있는 상황입니다.
then we need to use a cross mode but right now we just want to say we don't want to use ip mode
그렇다면 크로스 모드를 사용해야 하지만 지금은 IP 모드를 사용하고 싶지 않다고 말하고 싶습니다.
i keep uh ip and ip mode so that's why we don't want to change what we need to make here is just
나는 IP와 IP 모드를 유지하므로 여기서 우리가 만들어야하는 것을 변경하고 싶지 않은 이유는 다음과 같습니다.
make uh set that to never okay let's go ahead and save that
어, 그거 절대 안돼로 설정하고 저장합시다.
okay and then all we need to do then run calico apply next line number nine apply minus f and
좋아, 이제 옥양목을 실행하고 다음 줄에 9번을 적용하고 F를 빼고
the yaml file we just created so before doing that let's go ahead and take a look at the route
이 작업을 수행하기 전에 방금 만든 yaml 파일을 통해 경로를 살펴봅시다.
so i'm going to run watch rod minus n so this shows the current route and pay attention here
시계 막대 마이너스 N을 실행하여 현재 경로를 표시하고 여기에주의를 기울일 것입니다.
on this line where we are going across we're going across from one node to the other
우리가 건너가는 이 선에서 우리는 한 노드에서 다른 노드로 건너가고 있습니다.
like we have a pod that's making a service call from one node to the other as
한 노드에서 다른 노드로 서비스 호출을 하는 파드가 있는 것처럼.
if you remember we're going through the tunnel because that's i be using ip and ip mode
우리가 터널을 통과하고 있다는 것을 기억한다면, 나는 IP와 IP 모드를 사용하고 있기 때문이다.
so if we now go ahead and run this just make sure and then we see
이제 이것을 실행하면 다음과 같이 표시됩니다.
how the route changes here for this line so let's let's go ahead and run that
이 라인의 경로가 어떻게 바뀌는지 확인해 보겠습니다.
and then you'll see the changed now it changed from uh the tunnel into at zero so it's actually
그러면 이제 터널에서 0으로 변경된 것을 볼 수 있으므로 실제로는 다음과 같습니다.
everything now is going through the regular interface so you're not going through the tunnel
이제 모든 것이 일반 인터페이스를 통과하므로 터널을 통과하지 않습니다.
and that's the change that we just made so we made that from ip full ip and ip to regular because
이것이 우리가 방금 변경 한 것이므로 전체 IP 및 IP에서 일반 IP로 변경했습니다.
um the the reason for this because both these servers are on the same subnet so there is no
그 이유는이 두 서버가 동일한 서브넷에 있기 때문에
reason for us to be using the ip and ip so make this a lot faster so if you are in a situation
우리가 IP와 IP를 사용하는 이유 그래서 이것을 훨씬 더 빠르게 만들 수 있으므로 상황에 처한 경우
where you have all your servers running on the same subnet then just you can go ahead and change
모든 서버가 동일한 서브넷에서 실행되는 경우 계속해서 변경할 수 있습니다.
that from ip in ip into direct basically so you're not going through ip and ip mode
기본적으로 IP에서 IP로 직접 연결하므로 IP와 IP 모드를 거치지 않아도 됩니다.
so now let's verify that we don't see ip and ip at all in the packet so we're gonna do another
이제 패킷에 IP와 IP가 전혀 표시되지 않는지 확인해 보겠습니다.
uh packet capturing and then we'll see verify that we don't see ip and ip so i'm here in the visual
패킷을 캡처한 다음 IP와 IP가 보이지 않는지 확인해 보겠습니다.
city command line so let's go ahead and run take a look at the pods again and see um so we have
도시 명령줄을 실행해서 파드를 다시 한번 살펴보자.
four parts if you recall we have two of them running on master this guy and this guy
네 부분으로 나뉘어져 있고, 그 중 두 개는 마스터 이 녀석과 이 녀석에서 실행 중입니다.
and these two in between they're running on node one so i'm going to
그리고 그 사이에 있는 이 두 개는 1번 노드에서 실행 중이므로
go inside sh inside one of these uh pods on the master node so i'm going to sh in here
마스터 노드에 있는 이 파드들 중 하나에 들어가서 여기에 들어가겠습니다.
and then i'm going to call a service
그리고 나서 서비스를 호출할거야.
which is on the other node so and then we can then capture the the packets and see
다른 노드에 있으므로 패킷을 캡처하여 다음을 확인할 수 있습니다.
how it's going let's go ahead and let's search into that okay and before running
어떻게 진행 중인지 살펴보고 실행하기 전에
calling the service that is go ahead and do the run the capture command and let's go ahead and
서비스를 호출하는 서비스를 호출하고 캡처 명령을 실행하고 계속해서
now call this service and as you can see the the packets have been captured let's go out and let me
이제 이 서비스를 호출하고 보시다시피 패킷이 캡처되었습니다.
exit all of that and then maximize this let's go ahead up and verify the package from the beginning
이 모든 것을 종료한 다음 최대화해서 처음부터 패키지를 확인하겠습니다.
and do a kind of comparison like we had before so again the the packets always include the internet
그리고 아까 했던 것처럼 일종의 비교를 해서 다시 한번 패킷에 항상 인터넷이 포함되어 있는지 확인합니다.
packet which includes everything uh its ip and other information inside that so this is the
모든 것을 포함하는 패킷과 그 안의 IP 및 기타 정보를 포함하므로 이것이 바로
ethernet frame nothing is shared there as before
이더넷 프레임 이전처럼 아무것도 공유되지 않습니다.
however in here we'll see that now the source is this the server itself calling into so going from
그러나 여기서는 이제 소스가 서버 자체에서 호출하는 것이므로
the server because you're going through the regular interface so this service called directly
일반 인터페이스를 통해 서버를 호출하기 때문에 이 서비스는 직접 호출합니다.
into the ip address of the uh of the pod previously this first the other
이전에는 파드의 어의 IP 주소로 먼저 다른
packet ip packet had the source as one server calling the other server and then inside that
패킷 IP 패킷의 소스가 한 서버가 다른 서버를 호출하고 그 내부에서
if you recall this saw and there was an ip in ip but that doesn't exist anymore so this is actually
만약 당신이 이것을 기억한다면 IP에 IP가 있었지만 더 이상 존재하지 않으므로 실제로 이것은
there of just only one ethernet packet and everything else there's no ip in ip anymore
이더넷 패킷이 하나만 있고 다른 모든 것은 더 이상 IP에 IP가 없습니다.
and then the next step is basically uh the tcp so there is no uh ip in ip packet that
그리고 다음 단계는 기본적으로 어, tcp이므로 어, IP 패킷에 IP가 없습니다.
we saw previously in the previous capture we'll see it doesn't exist anymore because
이전 캡처에서 보았듯이 더 이상 존재하지 않는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
we are not using ip in ip anymore so basically this is regular um ip and then this is a destination
우리는 더 이상 IP에서 IP를 사용하지 않으므로 기본적으로 이것은 일반 음 IP이고 이것은 목적지입니다.
of the uh the pod that you're calling the service that you're calling um so that's that's it so um
당신이 호출하고있는 서비스를 호출하는 파드의 음이므로 그게 다입니다.
i hope you enjoyed this um presentation i'm going to summarize next and then we go from there
이 음 프레젠테이션을 즐기 셨기를 바랍니다. 다음에 요약하고 거기서부터 시작하겠습니다.
so in this video we covered the following topics we started with take a look we took a look at
이 비디오에서 우리는 다음과 같은 주제를 다루었습니다. 우리가 살펴본 것을 살펴보십시오.
container network interface i covered this in extensively in my first and second
컨테이너 네트워크 인터페이스 1편과 2편에서 광범위하게 다루었습니다.
series of this course so if you want more information go ahead and check those
시리즈에서 자세히 다루었으니, 더 자세한 정보를 원하신다면
we also introduced project calico which is a cni it's one of the choices that you can make as far
우리는 또한 당신이 지금까지 할 수있는 선택 중 하나 인 CNI 인 프로젝트 캘리코를 소개했습니다.
as selecting a cni provider for for your project we looked at ip and ip protocol what it is and how
프로젝트에 대한 CNI 제공 업체를 선택함에 따라 IP 및 IP 프로토콜이 무엇이며 어떻게 사용되는지 살펴 보았습니다.
calico uses it we learned about border gate protocol which is an important topic in using
캘리코는 이를 사용하여 보더 게이트 프로토콜을 사용하는 데 중요한 주제인 보더 게이트 프로토콜에 대해 배웠습니다.
when you use calico and how it's been leveraging calico we also discussed various network choices
캘리코를 사용할 때와 캘리코를 어떻게 활용했는지, 그리고 다양한 네트워크 선택에 대해서도 논의했습니다.
and when to use which we also learned how to make a network change after calico is installed
그리고 언제 사용하는지, 그리고 캘리코를 설치한 후 네트워크를 변경하는 방법도 배웠습니다.
and the last thing thank you so much for your time if you like it please give it a like and
그리고 마지막으로 시간 내 주셔서 감사합니다 마음에 드시면 좋아요를 눌러주세요.
consider subscribing i have the other courses that you might be interested especially in networking
구독을 고려하십시오 특히 네트워킹에 관심이있을 수있는 다른 과정이 있습니다.
i have two more courses i'll include these courses um names and a link in the description below
두 개의 강좌가 더 있습니다. 아래 설명에 이 강좌의 이름과 링크를 포함하겠습니다.
so again thank you so much and please take care
다시 한번 감사드리며 조심하세요.